Preliminary Inventory to the Council on International and Public Affairs (CIPA) and Bhopal Resource Action Center Records TAM.554
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Council on International and Public Affairs (CIPA) and Bhopal Resource Action Center Records
circa 1970-2005
1980-2000
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Council on International and Public Affairs (U.S.)
Bhopal Action Resource Center
Oppenheim, Carolyn Toll
Morehouse, Ward, 1929-
TAM.554
36.5 Linear Feet (37 boxes)
The Council on International and Public Affairs (CIPA) was founded in 1954 as a nonprofit human rights, education, research and publishing group, with an international outlook, and with a particular emphasis on corporate accountability and social responsibility, prompted in part by the Bhopal, India disaster occurred in 1984 at a Union Carbide Pesticide plant in which a leak of toxic gas killed some 8,000 people immediately, a like number in succeeding years, and caused thousands of permanent disabilities, notably blindness. The collection contains CIPA minutes, annual and financial reports, reports on various issues, topics, and files on CIPA projects and sponsored organizations, notably in relation to the Bhopal, India Union Carbide Industrial Accident, including records of the Bhopal Action Resource Center. Bhopal-related materials include reports, legal and government documents and clippings. There are also records of the Intermediate Technology Development Group, a development organization that advocates and promotes technology that enriches and benefits the lives of poor people, and publications, reports and articles of CIPA founder Ward Morehouse.
Box 1-37
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Carolyn Oppenheim and Ward Morehouse on behalf of the Council on International Public Affairs (CIPA). The accession number associated with this collection is 2010.076.
Arrangement
This collection is unprocessed.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Council on International and Public Affairs (CIPA) was founded in 1954 as a nonprofit human rights, education, research and publishing group, with an international outlook, and with a particular emphasis on corporate accountability and social responsibility, prompted in part by the Bhopal, India disaster occurred in 1984 at a Union Carbide Pesticide plant in which a leak of toxic gas killed some 8,000 people immediately, a like number in succeeding years, and caused thousands of permanent disabilities, notably blindness.
CIPA has sponsored various projects and organizations, notably the Bhopal Resource Action Center, the International Coalition for Justice in Bhopal (ICJB), Apex Press (its publishing arm), as well as the Program on Corporations, Law and Democracy (POCLAD), the Intermediate Technology Development Group, and the Global Information Network (GIN), a distributor of developing country news services. CIPA also seeks remedies for human rights violations, primarily by exposing the roots of corporate power in the U.S. and worldwide. Ward Morehouse (b. 1929), CIPA's founder and now its president emeritus, taught Political Science at New York University and has been a Visiting Professor at the University of Lund in Sweden and the Administrative Staff College of India in Hyderabad. He has also been a consultant to various United Nations agencies, and is the author or editor of some twenty books, including Building Sustainable Communities, The Bhopal Tragedy, Abuse of Power: The Social Performance of Multinational Corporations, Worker Empowerment in a Changing Economy, and The Underbelly of the U.S. Economy. A resident of Northampton, MA, Morehouse is also a co-founder of the Western Massachusetts Committee on Corporations and Democracy with his wife, Carolyn Toll Oppenheim, CIPA's interim Executive Director and a former journalist and journalism professor.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains CIPA minutes, annual and financial reports, reports on various issues, topics, and files on CIPA projects and sponsored organizations, notably in relation to the Bhopal, India Union Carbide Industrial Accident, including records of the Bhopal Action Resource Center. Bhopal-related materials include reports, legal and government documents and clippings. There are also records of the Intermediate Technology Development Group, a development organization that advocates and promotes technology that enriches and benefits the lives of poor people, and publications, reports and articles of CIPA founder Ward Morehouse.
Hazardous wastes -- Environmental aspects.; Corporate power.; Business and politics.; Employee rights.; Human rights.; Developing countries |x Foreign economic relations.; Developing countries |x Economic conditions.; Right to refuse hazardous work.; Biotechnology |x Social aspects.; Bhopal Union Carbide Plant Disaster, Bhopal, India, 1984.; Social responsibility of business.; Bhopal Action Resource Center; Morehouse, Ward, 1929-; Union Carbide Corporation; International Coalition for Justice in Bhopal; Council on International and Public Affairs (U.S.); Union Carbide Ltd. (India); Council on International and Public Affairs (U.S.); Oppenheim, Carolyn Toll; Oppenheim, Carolyn Toll; Morehouse, Ward, 1929-
- Bhopal Disaster Publications, 1984-2005 (Box 1)
- Bhopal Disaster Articles and Clippings (A-L), 1984-2005 (Box 2)
  General
  Sorted alphabetically by publication name. One folder per publication.
- Bhopal Articles and Clippings (M-W), 1984-2005 (Box 3)
- International Coalition for Justice in Bhopal (ICJB); ICJB Victims Tour; UCC Perspectives, 1980s (Box 4)
  International Coalition for Justice in Bhopal (ICJB). Union Carbide Corporation (UCC)
- International Coalition for Justice in Bhopal (ICJB) India and U.S.: Correspondence, Letters, Activism, Bhopal Citizens Commission, 1984-1990s (Box 5)
- International Coalition for Justice in Bhopal (ICJB) Correspondence and Reports, Late 1980s-1990s (Box 6)
  NGOs and groups involved international justice for justice in Bhopal.
- Reports, Articles and Correspondence, 1980s-1990s (Box 7)
  Full folder of NYTimes articles and correspondence between CIPA and NYTimes. PPT- Permanent People's Tribunal Delhi 1992.
- Bhopal Court Documents, Government Reports, Union Carbide Corporation Annual Stockholder Meetings (Multiple Meetings), 1980s-1990s (Box 8)
  U.S. Senate Hazards Right to Know hearings. Ginsburg Report Formosa Plastics: Glaveston Plastics - Texas
- International Coalition for Justice in Bhopal (ICJB) Documents, Correspondence, Late 1980s (Box 9)
  Union Carbide West Virginia plant info. Analysis of UCC. Texas brain tumor research. OSHA reports related to Bhopal and toxins.
- Bhopal Action Resource Center (BARC); International Coalition for Justice in Bhopal (ICJB) (Box 10)
  Bhopal Action Resource center (BARC)
- Bhopal Action Resource Center (BARC): Bhopal Legal Documents, Court Transcripts, U.S. and India, 1984-2000 (Box 11)
  UCC Financial Info. Other misc.
- Bhopal Action Resource Center (BARC): Media Clippings, Articles; Bhopal Legal Documents and Medical Reports and Articles, 1985-1987 (Box 12)
- Bhopal Action Resource Center (BARC) Documents, 1980s (Box 13)
  Bhopal Action Resource Center (BARC)
- Reports, Dissertations and Other Writing on Bhopal -- Legal, Toxic Issues., 1983-2005 (Box 14)
  Sorted by author or publication name.
- Legal Documents, Reports, 1984-1990s (Box 15)
- Bhopal Reports on Permanent People's Tribunal: Legal Documents, 1980s (Box 16)
- Medical and Legal Reports and Court Transcripts; Bhopal Activism., 1984-1990 (Box 17)
- Bhopal Documents and Medical Reports from India., 1980s (Box 18)
- Union Carbide-Related Documents, 1980s-1990s (Box 19)
- CIPA: Permanent Peoples Tribunal; Several Peoples' Tribunals on Corporations, Human Rights, Bhopal and More., 1980s; 1990s (Box 20)
  CIPA report on: Permanent Peoples' Tribunal on Global Corporations and Human Wrongs, 22-25 March, 2005. University of Warvick, Coventry, UK
- Permanent Peoples' Tribunals on Bhopal and Other Areas, 1980s-1990s (Box 21)
  Popular forums. United Nations. Citizens resistance to toxins. Corporate analysis. Enron.
- Biotechnology, Corporate Power, Technology Development, United Nations, 1970-2005 (Box 22)
  Publications and articles. Also: David Dembo and Clarence J. Dias. Unido studies. Third World Affairs 1985 (WM and DD)
- Program on Corporations, Law and Democracy (POCLAD) Newsletters (By What Authority); Margold Report--NAACP., 1980s; 1990s (Box 23)
  Legal and labor documents. International Secondary Education. Church Proxy Solutions. Program on Corporations, Law and Democracy (POCLAD).
- Environmental, Hazardous and Biotech Activities, Reports and Papers by CIPA and Others, 1980s (Box 24)
  Hazardous Substances Export Policy (SEP). PANNA (Pesticide Action Network North America) correspondence, reports and activism. Research on Monsanto, Genex Corporation. INFACT reports on corporate power.
- Superfund. Workers Hazards and Unemployment, 1980s, 1990s (Box 25)
- Reports and Papers on Biotechnology and its Legal and Third World Impacts and Related Issues; Superfund Documents, 1980-1990s (Box 26)
  CIPA, Ward Morehouse, David Dembo, Clarence Dias
- CIPA Reports for United Nations Industrial Development Organization (UNIDO); Other Writing on Science, Technology and Biotechnology., 1980s (Box 27)
  United Nations Industrial Development Organization (UNIDO)
- Biotechnology Reports, Papers and Research Documents, 1980s (Box 28)
  International Center for Law and Development. Center for Science, Technology and Developement.
- Activism on Biotech, Toxics and Right to Know. Bhopal Related EPA Report 1985. Rachel's Weekly 1991-1992, 1980s, 1990s (Box 29)
  EPA Guidelines on Chemical Safety (1985) just immediately after Bhapal chemical spill and before the U.S. Community Right to Know Law. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA).
- Underbelly of the U.S. Economy; Working papers on Unemployment, Labor and the U.S. Economy., 1980s, 1990s (Box 30)
- Corporations, Too Much Newsletters, Permanent Peoples' Tribunal, 1980s, 1990s (Box 31)
  CIPA reports. "A Perilous Partnership- The UN Development Programme's Flirtation with Corporate Collaboration"- TRAC- The Transnational Resource & Action Center- In collaboration with the Institute for Policy Studies and CIPA. UNIDO report: "Technology Trends Series- Trends in Biotechnology Development & Transfer". D. Dembo and W. Morehouse. Media Source Guide on US-China Relations- 1983 (CIPA). Book: "Not in my Backyard" by Jane Anne Morris - 1994- ISBN 97809624574
- Organizing Material to Resist Corporate Abuse of Power, 2000s (Box 32)
- Communities Concerned about Corporations (CCC): Reports, Writings and Correspondence, 1990s (Box 33)
  POCLAD poster: 'A Call to Defy Corporate Domination"
- VHS Videos and Audio Cassettes, 1980s, 1990s (Box 34)
- Council on International and Public Affairs (CIPA) Annual Reports: 1977-2005; Board Meetings: 1995-2009, 1979-2009 (Box 35)
  National Jobs for All Coalition (NJFAC): Pamphlets, newsletters and envelopes "Drive for Decent Work"
- Council on International and Public Affairs (CIPA) Board Meetings, 1978-1994 (Box 36)
- Council on International and Public Affairs (CIPA) Board Meetings, Notes, Correspondence and Annual Reports, 1979-2000 (Box 37)
  Intermediate Technology Development Group - North America (ITDG N/A)